welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
all right um so welcome to the stoa
uh peter or some of the other uh regular
stewards of the stoa aren't with us
today um but but yeah i just wanted to
kind of first off just
send in a pre give some appreciation to
uh them for creating this
space for us to be able to explore
together um and
uh yeah so today we're gonna be talking
about um
sutra to tantra um and uh i won't go
into too much more i'll just maybe hand
things off to charlie here
uh and uh yeah we'll jump straight into
it thanks jared
so the the topic today sutra to tantra
is quite neat at least at first glance
it's quite neat
it's good to see so many of you here and
interested
i think it does have relevance for
anybody who's meditating
and if you're interested in
understanding your meditation from
perspective of its principle and how it
functions
physically mentally in relation with
other people and with the environment
how meditation practice functions
has as much to do with the mental
framework and with the worldview
that is the the frame of reference
within which you're practicing
as it does with the mechanics of the
practice itself
and i think that's sometimes hidden
so i wanted to say that what we're
starting out with today
is presenting an approach it's a
perspective
not a universal truth
and looking from this perspective
there are no universal truths
this perspective is rooted in a small
and very late development of buddhism
called zogchen which
some of you will be familiar with and
zogten has been hashed around
and interpreted in multiple ways so
the pers the perspective that we're
going to present today it may or may not
sound familiar to you
depending on your background and
depending on what your experience has
been and your own particular path
so this approach is certainly quite
different to the
underlying framework and practice
of many meditation methods including
secular meditations
and i think that is possibly where the
interest is coming from as well
so sometimes what happens when i'm
presenting this view is that somebody
will ask well what about x
you know what about the four noble
truths or what about the original
words of the buddha or what about the
anapanasati sutra
or whatever so i just want to give a
heads up
that my reply is always going to be
something like from this perspective
x looks like this or looks like that or
is irrelevant maybe
so those kind of questions are great for
clarification and for figuring out how
these the different possible frames of
reference
function and how they can be useful in
our lives
and the perspective specifically it's
buddhist tantra
as seen through the zogchen lens
and what matters from that perspective
is congruence and fit
so we're going to be emphasizing
appropriate application in context
not codes of right or wrong that's
the way that this perspective looks at
activity and practice and meditation as
well
so
the intention of the the intention of
the session is twofold
it's to present a particular view and
it's for you
to be able to explore what that means
and what kind of impact that view could
have on your life and on your meditation
practice and on the interconnectivity
and relationship of those two in
practice
so in a while i'm going to give a brief
outline of buddhist sutra from this
perspective and
particularly i really wanted to say
something about
how to understand that a salient in
practice because it's not really
possible to move between the two
frameworks of sutra
and tantra and to consciously have them
as frameworks of reference without
clearly seeing the stance
associated with sutra which is dualist
and that is the aspect that is often
unacknowledged or unseen
in in practice
so uh the the other thing i want to say
here is that we're
starting out with quite a bit of
buddhist terminology
and as the group progresses i think
we'll transition from using
quite so much jargon um
but i wanted to be clear as well that
what we're possibly going to attempt
here
as a community of practice which asanga
in buddhist terms is an orchestrated
transition and so
understanding where ideas come from and
understanding the lineage
of ideas the lineage of knowledge and
practice
i think that's much much more important
than our
culture generally and currently
recognizes
and so in relation to meditation
including secular meditation including
mindfulness
insight meditation vipassana many of the
practices that you'll find if you decide
you want to start
meditation there are attitudes and
applications and effects that are rooted
in buddhist sutra and in adaptations of
buddhist sutra
and they're not always apparent or
obvious and it can be very helpful i
think
untangling those frames of reference
when you want to
consciously adapt your practice
so i think that's that's enough as a
short introduction and jared
i think it would be great to hear you
speak and to hear you say something
about
how you came to be here and
something about your own practice as
well
yeah yeah um well let's see here
i guess uh this
um the sutra to tantra uh
speaking of it as a bit of a transition
uh is very alive for me because i feel
like i'm kind of going through it right
now
um and when i think about it from a bit
of a
high level um i realized that one of the
most predominant qualities
is that the sutra perspective
uh really emphasis emphasizes
renunciation a lot right it's it's um
uh it tends to look at uh
the form or the material world uh with a
very with a cautious
cautious uh perspective uh you know
maybe there's some danger there
uh to be kind of lost in uh
in delusion or something um maybe many
many different things i suppose
um or or a self maybe is the predominant
thing
um but as i've started to
engage more with practice from the
tantric perspective another interesting
thing here is that
technically i'm not doing a lot of
specifically
tantric practices they're more zogen uh
oriented practices from the zogchen
perspective um
and charlie's gonna jump in here and
correct me when i when i say something
that's completely
in the wrong place but um uh you know
it's it's
um this my relationship with my own
senses and emotions and things that i
used to be very cautious about
uh are starting to um convert to being a
little bit more uh
kind of passionately engaged and kind of
appreciative
um and um yeah
it's refreshing uh and and yet there's
still this kind of background
noise of of this kind of renunciative
frame of reference that so many of the
teachings that i spend time with
uh predominantly vipassana and shamatha
that that still kind of influence uh the
way that
uh the way that i sit even when i'm
doing or the way that i engage with my
relationships
um or the the decisions i make and
how i uh how i live life and
you know my career decisions and
everything so it's i think
the biggest thing here is that uh
it it's kind of all pervasive uh you
know i think charlie and i have
mentioned before that
sutra is kind of like the the metaphor
of the water that we're surrounded by
that we're unaware
of if you're a fish you know it's like
there's a lot of citric water
that i was never aware of and now i've
only started to kind of
uh get a sense for um and so that that
transition is
is uh is exciting and interesting and um
and yet also very like bright and aware
i used to feel like when
when i was having
experiences or phases of my practice
that seemed to be working really well
i was kind of removed a little bit from
the world like a little very airy very
light
and now all of a sudden things are
becoming a little bit more embodied and
kind of
real and tactile and and deeply engaged
with the material world as well
so yeah i don't know there's there's a
few few of my reflections of just like
the felt
sense and reframing of a lot of my my
practice uh in in off the cushion
um so yeah i don't know anything charlie
coming up there is uh
you wanted to double click on um
thanks jared i think that was a really
great um
personal explanation of of how practice
can change
and and can change every very short time
as well
um
if you were to consider
a phrase or a couple of words that would
kind of encapsulate that what would you
say how would you describe
the difference in the in what has
happened say
mentally or in terms of your perspective
do you think something's changed in that
way
um
yeah i don't know it i guess a biggest
part is
is there is a
it felt like kind of going in from from
having my my practice have a very strict
container of where it can be practiced
and and
where where it's right and where it's
wrong uh to being far more open
uh to kind of all of the circumstances
that arise um
and and not feeling nice have a lot of
like judging
uh over you know this emotional reaction
that i had i'm like oh that was a bad
one i better
look at something there needs to be
worked with so yeah it's like
a little bit more accepting a little bit
more all-encompassing
and it makes it that much easier for me
to really apply it
right yeah something that i've noticed
about the way that you
have changed over the last year is that
your language has changed
when you're talking about your practice
you're talking about your meditation
practice
and if i remember correctly i think
you used to ask
things like should i do this is that
right
is this the right thing and
that has kind of subtly changed in some
way um
yeah yeah now if
if i were to characterize what i'm more
interested in it is
less should have and more of what am i
not noticing you know like
what else is there where where else
should i be looking
um what what's what's being missed or
where can i
more deeply engage and i remember you
describing
a real revelatory moment as well which
is fabulous when that
happens in meditation i think a lot of
people here probably relate
to that too do you want to say something
about that
this in the the shenae yeah
um yeah so so
i guess to put a little context so i
practiced
shamatha meditation for about a year um
and pretty aggressively in the sense
that it was you know a minimum of an
hour
a day but usually two hours a day and
then that culminated in a 10-day retreat
and i kind of came out of that
uh gutting a lot getting a lot of
traction on it um but still kind of like
noticing there's this
a lot of um
constriction i guess in in the approach
and toward that the tail end things
might started
might have started to open up and i had
a few experiences that felt very clear
um but when i started practicing shine
which is
a very similar practice and the result
is this is supposed to be
a deep appreciation of emptiness in the
same sense that
uh shamatha does uh but it's from his
own gen perspective so it excludes
nothing
um and so so yeah i i feel like i've
gotten to similar
uh moments of of clarity but when they
come from a very unrestricted
approach of shine of not having any
preference about what is in your
experience
um when that clarity arose it was kind
of all pervading
um and and and i guess
speaking to um this this idea of
of solidness or being back down to earth
uh you know
this this moment of of really kind of
tapping
into uh the empty aspect of my
experience
that was kind of pervading and including
all of my sensory experiences instead of
just my breath or just the sensations at
my nose or something like that
um that like it felt like i was
so unbelievably embodied you know i was
like i'm so solid i was like as
solid as a rock or something like that
um and there was no boundary to the
to the state as well um and and the the
the
naturalness of this condition
uh it was so much less uh manufactured
uh that it felt so much more wholesome
uh and it didn't really have as much of
the striving that
had been part of the shamatha
approach as well um yeah i don't know i
don't know i have
super specifically when i go in but it's
kind of comparing these two different
uh practices which are actually aimed at
a very similar result but come from this
radically different stances as we're
talking here whether it's the sutrix
stance
or the do you do you think that do you
think the result is similar or
you know we go backwards and forwards
over this i think in some ways it's
if the result is no self or
an experience of the world as
illusory which is sometimes given as a
result then i think
the experience of the result can be
quite different
it's not to make a judgment about either
of those but
that the actual embodied experience or
disembodied experience can be
can be quite yeah well
uh the the the more no selfie
experiences that i had
actually were outside of meditation
previous to
doing tantra um so when i'm talking
about shamatha uh you know
i think you know i i never was never a
master of shamatha and i'm
by no means a master of shine but i
guess i feel like i've arrived at a
similar
um glimpses of of what
uh possibility there they have they hold
in their kind of ultimate manifestation
right
um and the funny thing is that when i
had this
glimpse in in uh shamatha of like
clarity in a very specific location
um i it was kind of like oh well that
was kind of cool uh
and and i got off my cushion and and
things kind of went back to normal quite
quite quick uh whereas when uh after
getting up from
from that uh practice of shine um
you know it was like the the residue of
that state was
was you know carried very directly with
me uh it was it was not like something
that would just kind of instantly vanish
uh and i think this had to do with that
unconstructed nature
uh and so so the profundity of the of
the uh
of the sheena experience seem to be
quite uh
quite i guess literally bigger uh more
spacious
uh um although i you know i'm open to
the to
uh to thinking that um if i were to
continue practicing
uh shamatha you know things could open
up and become less constricted
uh if you continue to go down that path
yeah i think the paths are very
different yeah
there is really no path with the shine
which is also something that has been
uh terrifying in the beginning because i
didn't know
what the hell i was doing you know i had
a lot of like moments of like
i've been meditating for six years what
is what am i doing i have no idea what
i'm doing i'm not following the
instructions
uh whereas when you have your very
concrete maps and step-by-step
instructions
uh you know it's quite quite easy to
feel okay with where you're
at i suppose but also at the same time
because it's like you have such a clear
vision of where you're going
um and that creates all this kind of
stride and future focus
that's interesting i think maybe i could
say something about that in relation to
the difference between
sutra and tantra from this perspective
so buddhist tantra moves from the
abstract to the specific
it's a contextualizing application so
where sutra is global
and has general solutions tantra is
always local
and detailed so um so however nuance and
contextualize your practices your
or your world view if you apply tantric
practice
and view then that's going to further
contextualize it
and the thing about that is that it's an
infinite process there's no end point
there's no final state whereas the
citric perspective is that
you are working gradually towards a
final state
that's a very different nuance to the
the way that the practice works
and so the contextualization is the
mechanism by which it's going to reveal
and challenge and what it challenges is
your
sacred cows so you may
you might have heard tantra sometimes
classified as a dangerous path or a fast
path and i think that is what's
dangerous about it it's threatening
your unseen assumptions and motivations
because it's going to uncover them it's
like
knowing the territory understanding the
territory
it reveals the rigidity of the map so
vadriana practice reveals your sacred
cows and in revealing them there's this
threat
because once you your hidden frames of
reference
are transparent once your your
motivations become transparent they kind
of
they just cease to function in the same
way
they can't function in the way that they
were functioning when
they were unseen so tantric practice has
this derailing effect
and i think that's sometimes why it's
considered dangerous or challenging or
threatening
but it doesn't it doesn't need to be
terrifying it's not
something that you can force either that
is just a very natural
result of the practice method
yeah well and it's not always
destructive in the sacred cows it can
also be
destructive in the things that are kind
of holding us back right so it's like
right right
you know right my anger so much of my
early
uh early path was being really obsessed
with all of these maps of awakening and
thinking oh i must be
well no where did you get which stage
did you get oh god
uh well uh i guess oh sorry that's it
well at first i thought i was a buddha
you know of course when i when i
had this first experience i was like oh
well this is enlightenment right uh
and then i was like oh shit that wasn't
it at all uh man i got a long ways to go
um so so yeah somewhere in the
the middle of of uh that of somewhere
after stream entry and
before uh uh our hot
whatever yeah i don't know this is the
weird thing right like
the more i became engaged with tantra
the more i genuinely like i used to kind
of play act being like well i'm not
really interested in the maps
um because i knew that there could be a
limitation and i could say that but i
didn't really mean it like it was still
kind of always in the back of my head of
kind of
you know trying to size myself up but
but now i really have very little
interest and i think part of it is
because as you say
there's such an individualized and
personalized component here where it's
like
i know that there's no map that can
describe what my
uh what my non-dual nature will look
like
it's something that has to be kind of
very specifically discovered
um and that that's been liberating in
the sense of like not having to
hold myself to some external
expectations i suppose
[Music]
you know thinking about sacred cows i
think the
in some sense the biggest sacred
character of all is the seriousness with
which we take ourselves
you know and we're very important of
course naturally because we're
the center of our own universes and
in buddhist terms like with the center
of our own mandalas
but uh
we decided to use this phrase but um
degenerate fuckwits
in the introduction because uh i felt
that it was really important that
anybody
who wasn't really in a position to be
able to laugh at themselves or
just not able to go there at the moment
deselect themselves
from coming because the psychological
starting point
for tantric practice is that you really
you need enough self-confidence and
stability of self that you're able to
just be playful with yourself and laugh
at yourself a bit
um no that doesn't discount being
serious and it doesn't mean
becoming excruciatingly self-deprecating
as a default mode but
because of this contextualizing move in
tantric practice
your your unseen sacredness of self is
going to loosen up a little bit
as well i think
well this kind of speaks to to um
the the kind of like you said the base
or the entry point of tantra is this
emptiness
um and i know i you know i think i've
heard a lot like you know the
the kind of phrase that the dharma is
also empty um
and it's one thing to say it but it's a
different thing for
uh tantra to be practiced from that
perspective where all of these
uh is radically empty in the sense that
it's hard to take anything radically
serious
uh or maybe it's maybe not serious but
you know take it extremely serious but
not literal uh
and if you can if you're not taking it
literal then you can there could be a
sense of humor or something i don't know
something something about that dialectic
that seems important
so maybe i was going to say something
about sutriana
specifically and talk a little bit about
that should we go on to that now
yeah i did see a couple of things coming
out okay
maybe we have some questions then that
tantra might be similar to have a look
at the chat
yeah we're doing over there
yeah does that is tantra seems similar
to zen uh
is that is that that uh ring true to you
charlie
what is the question sorry if sutra is
or if contra is similar to zen is tantra
similar to zen
zen is in some ways more similar to zog
chan i think
uh and it shares roots with zog chan
um there is the
you know in shikhanta as a practice i'm
not a zen practitioner but
the just sitting and the expansiveness
of that practice is
very similar to um the zorchem
perspective
towards the starting point of emptiness
the
the um the preliminary of emptiness if
you like
so i think there are similarities there
and i think there are historical
crossovers as well um zen
my correct me if i'm wrong al but my
understanding is that zen
is more oriented towards emptiness
tantra is oriented towards form and and
movement
so it's it's always discovering the
empty quality or the nebulosity of form
and movement and relationship
my understanding is that zen is much
more specifically oriented to
emptiness
so i'm saying it's largely largely
correct i think
oh yeah you have the chat open as well i
have the chat here yeah
there's yeah
a great chat there's lots going on in
there really interesting
thank you for contributing everyone um
i'll say something about sutriana um
jana sanskrit for path vehicle
um sutra is like a set or a list or a
collection
it's usually a collection of rules or
guidances
and so sutrayana the path of sutra
from this perspective it it looks like a
path of renunciation
so a path is a framework of reference i
really like that
phrase to describe a path you know if
you think about it
literally you're on a path and then
everything you see
is angled from the perspective of your
position on that path the path
constrains your view and you you can
only see what you can see from that path
if you're on a different path your view
would be different you know
that's a very literal analogy it's very
simple but i think it
it works as a way to describe
how we are and how we live as well we're
all constrained
by the view from the particular path
that we've taken this
thus far and so when i talk about a
framework of reference
that's what i'm referring to it's
the framework of reference is synonymous
for
where we're at now in terms of world
view
and perspective and understanding of how
things work
and it's a really good idea
to know what your frame of reference is
and i think this is just getting
increasingly difficult
and confusing because of the
contemporary confluence of so many
different cultures and traditions and
practices
it's just really actually quite hard
to know and understand exactly where
you're
at usually this this frame of reference
that you have is
very easily occluded by all the
different practices and the different
approaches that are available
and some some of them you try them out
you know a ton of them you incorporate
different
practices from different traditions you
know you
try to figure out what works for you and
what doesn't work
and i think it's really good and useful
to do that and it's probably necessary
to do that but the downside is that it
can really occlude
where you're actually at it gives you
this false impression that you're moving
between
views and systems and references and it
gives you this
impression that you know you think
you're applying different methods in
different contexts
and the thing is that the application of
different methods is
almost always adapted into
and by a frame of reference that you're
not seeing
that it's like your operating system
it's like a world view or
an implicit understanding of how things
are
based on where you're at that's your
yarn that's your your path
so the the starting point of moving into
a new mode of practice
and view is that you want to stand where
you are now
and by that i mean you you want to know
your current framework of reference it's
not
about expressing values
it quite quite probably has nothing to
do with your conscious values or what
you think they are
it's about seeing those blind spots
and unless you've already put a lot of
work into that which of course
a lot of people do put a lot of work
into that and
and that begins to reveal your your
frame of reference but
unless you do that work i think your
your framework of reference is your
autopilot
it's mostly what you can't see
[Music]
yeah so i think when when it comes to
contemporary meditation and spiritual
activity for the most part
the water that everybody is swimming in
is dualist
sometimes it often looks like monism but
the associated activity
is it's nearly always dualist and it's
really conscious it's not
well understood so i i think i'd like to
spend a little bit more time talking
about
um how you recognize a dualist frame of
reference
um maybe dude are there any questions
from that last
little monologue
let's see here um
i'll start looking through i'm curious
do you just as a quick thing
the judeo-christian framework that the
west kind of has
uh do you think that that's a major part
of the influence
um yeah doing the sutrick as well and
yeah
yes i do yeah and very explicitly sutra
was adapted into
a judeo-christian framework david
my husband david has written about that
maybe somebody could uh find the links
and put them here to share
there's um in his series on
uh consensus buddhism there are some
pages on
how the uh the
current uh insight vipassana uh
um lineage of meditation was created and
that's actually
really interesting history i found that
fascinating to
to read thank you jake that's great
yeah so so there is this dualism there's
um
this this stance um
of dualism that i want to talk about a
little bit because i do think it's it's
very much tied up with the path
of sutra not the end point not the the
specified endpoint but the
path and the perspective the the whole
frame of reference
so
dualism it's a stance that polarizes
your worldview so it takes the world it
takes
being or reality or everything and it
splits it into two possibilities
and you usually get this this idea that
there's
a wholesome beneficial cooperative
um good
way of doing things and one polarity and
then there's this limited and
constrained and
undesirable um other way
and it's characterized by these
polarized opposites
um often they're they're contrasting
options are characterized in such a way
that they're
mutually exclusive and
there's a sense that it's better to fit
yourself into one mode
and and discard the other mode there's
usually some kind of tension or friction
in between those two options they're not
necessarily a continuum there's this
sense of them kind of
you know you have a choice and one is a
good choice and the other is
a not so good choice and i think you
know we just
love to do this because as humans we're
adapted
to differentiate and categorize in order
to make sense of things
and the most simple obvious the most
easy
the most primary way to do that is
a is a b is b a is not
b it's having this very distinct
separation and opposite it's very
it's a very familiar pattern very easy
to get caught up in that because it
simplifies things
makes things somehow seem a lot more
manageable
so related to that it has
and these are some of the ways that you
can recognize
dualism operating because we all do this
it's it's very very natural so it has
this
massively good feel-good factor
like it feels really good sometimes
or for a duration
it it permeates everything it permeates
psychology like you know you have this
type a type b
thinking fast and slow you know people
love to have
these polarized categories that we can
slot ourselves into
um i'm specifically taking this out of
buddhism and buddhist practice because
it for this to be pertinent
as activity it has to be really relevant
to
what we're doing with our time like what
we notice we're attracted to how we
think about things what kind of
framework
we would bring into this into our
understanding of the world
so some of some of the other ways that
you can recognize dualism
is it's appealing it it lacks
complications
it lacks complexity and nuance
it tends to attract a lot of
fans like you know you can get this kind
of culti
feel around dualist uh
propositions for uh dualist ways of
being
there's it's got this kind of right
wrong feeling to it's like purity versus
impurity
um and i think something that happens
when you begin to apply this
even unconsciously as a frame of
reference
you start applying this and living this
view somehow
you can notice yourself just beginning
to feel like a little bit
averse to people who seem to
embrace the wrong way like you feel
slightly morally superior because you
understand
the difference between this wholesome
cooperative collaborative good
way of being and then you know you don't
want to have that greedy
basic bad you know whatever the
behavioral split
happens to be so i and you know going
back to the
the judeo-christian influence dualism
really does have
big associations with guilt like
if you start feeling bad about feeling a
certain way or you feel
bad that you don't feel a certain way
and then you get all caught up with
justification because
as soon as you feel bad about feeling
something your brain starts wanting to
justify
why you feel that particular way because
that's just how you feel as you you
start justifying your activity yourself
you justify your thoughts or
you start justifying your decisions you
know if you meditate a lot
you get very used to noticing what and
how you're thinking
so you can actually if you look out for
it you could maybe hear this kind of
little
smiggly voice justifying if you're
thinking or feeling a certain way you
know i think we all do it
another another characteristic is
wanting other people to behave
and fit in with how you think they
should behave
it's very subtle
[Music]
i'm not talking in the general here like
you know yeah of course we all want the
world to be free of bad behavior
i'm talking about noticing how your
personal
attitude and thought patterns affect
your
relationship with the world
so it's like this way of thinking
and wanting it's wanting others to
behave in the way they should
and feeling kind of deeply annoyed when
they don't do what you want them to do
or they don't
say what you want them to say or respond
in the way that you want them to respond
this is really
fundamental it's really basic
it's really difficult sometimes even to
see how manipulative
this kind of attitude is this dualist
stance
and the the reason that it's
manipulative is that every
single individual has the same thing
going on so
you know if you if you get into that the
only
the only solution if you buy into that
way
of thinking and and
projecting then you're going to end up
bullying people
that that bullying is going to be
directed as much towards the parts of
yourself
that don't quite fit into this dualist
framework
as it is towards um trying to have
others behave and think in the way that
you want
the way that you want them to you know
people are always wrong on the internet
that one really gets me
so i'm curious so if this is this
renunciative thing is like you know get
off with the bad and and in with the the
good
the wholesome uh yeah and so much of
this is about preferences and decision
making
uh how does tantra operate from uh
the non-renunciative but the
transformative uh element like how does
how does that
operate i think it's about preferences
and decision making but it's also
a lot about noticing
i think you
the reason i want to emphasize the
noticing the dualism
and understanding this the sutra
perspective as well is that you can't
really apply tantra until that is there
and the time the tantric way of going
about things would be passionate
engagement
and you know it's this contextualizing
move
so yeah you're you're
moving towards relationship
with the world and with the environment
and with other people and passionate
engagement
so noticing in your
engagement what kind of flavor that has
could be very useful
can be really really really useful to
understand whether you're trying to
you really subtly whether you're trying
to actually manipulate a situation or
whether you are receptive
and engaged and allowing the situation
to unfold
and it seems especially from my
perspective too right
is you know it's so important that that
the foundation of emptiness is there is
because the passionate engagement is
kind of contained within the emptiness
right right impedance isn't there then
it's not it's not tantra and then
you know i think this is what some of
the
then we're kind of we're acting in duels
and whether we realize it or not i
suppose right
we have a preference yeah
yeah yeah i think there's often this
kind of assumption that the normal
default behavior is limited and
constrained and greedy
and mean and we live in this kind of
hobbyist world and
we're allowed to get each other and i
think that's you know sometimes dualism
comes from
that perspective and you know of course
we have both we we've adapted to be both
collaborative
and um contentious
i know we're we're getting a bit in it
would be good to move into some breakout
sessions do you have
uh yeah something do we do we want to
open up some some questions for a bit
and see
should we do that yeah yeah yeah i've
seen a few things but
there's been a lot of chat so if you do
have a question if you could just like
restate it oh
goodness i just i just saw the chat
there that's funny
um and then also if you're monitoring
the chat
a plus ones are always helpful as well
so that we can uh
you know find the signal
i'm not in your brain it's neither
that's so funny
uh would someone like to ask a question
what are you seeing there
you have a repost here so how does one
go meta and approach
dualism itself with a tantric attitude
is it dualism is dual zom just bad
and to be always avoided
from the tantric perspective the moment
you notice
dualism you want to drop it
let it go embrace the aspect that you're
noticing
is uh
that you're pushing away you've got to
obviously be sensible and sane and
cautious
and figure out how you can do that
in a safe and
useful way but yes it's helpful to
think about functionality as well like
what is the purpose
that dualism is serving here how is it
how is it being useful for me in this
situation what's its function what is it
protecting
so you can you can consciously ask
questions like that or you can
simply notice what's going on in your
body
that's very useful notice the sensation
that's occurring in the body
and just allow that to
do its own thing
yeah passionate engagement
all right another thing is to notice how
you talk
um so i was going to mention this um
this really typical uh
dualist mode of being with other people
it's kind of a clue
to uh that you might be behaving in a
or thinking in a duelist frame of
reference and
it's how when you're with people you
talk
about the out group so quite often in
wholesome groups with a very strong
dualist inclination you
there's this way of dissing someone
while being really nice about them
so you you're talking about this person
in such a positive way and
i'm pointing out how they kind of just
don't quite get it but
you know dualism requires that you
maintain the split
whilst continuing to manifest the good
holes inside of things
so that's how you do it you're really
really nice and kind of
just make sure that that person is in
the category that
you want them to be in so you know
that's so funny
well can i make a remark you know and
taoism
that they say that um what you call
doism is essential
or i call polarization it's essential to
thinking you know warm if you didn't
have water you wouldn't have cold
and then you wouldn't have temperature
that's that's not
polarization is somewhat different to
categorization
we do need to categorize that's for sure
and categorization is always
pretty useful yeah
that um you know
i think i think that's the first thing
yeah i think it's possible to move
beyond that and have a little more
complexity and nuance that's maybe the
first thing that we start to do
i don't know
we have a number of people looking to uh
talk about applied practice
or practice to pointers and i think we
even mentioned uh
leading us in some applied practice uh
and this was actually something that you
and i talked about of
like uh whether or not to do guided uh
some
sort of guided thing so that might be
something fun to open up do you want to
say something about that jared
i i don't know uh
nothing well i i guess i'll say this in
the sense that uh
i've had my
my interest in guiding meditations has
largely subsided in the sense that
um again since it's such a personalized
exploration
uh it's it's harder to to fit into
because
you know in a similar way a guiding is
is kind of creating the structure
uh for for the meditation itself it's
kind of directing it and having
preference
um so i haven't been as much into
uh the guided element and yet i feel
the core intentions and stances uh as
being kind of the predominant
uh area of investigation and kind of
trying to
to see clear sealy because or see
clearly because
uh that seems seems to be what has the
biggest effect on my practice but maybe
you could
also shortly introduce sh shenae if if
that's
i don't know whatever whatever's up for
you right um
something to say about guided practice
is that that really
really works for sutrix styled
meditations because
sutra is general and the same thing
applies to everybody
the the the movement and tantra is more
and more and more personalized because
it's contextual
so there's a certain point where doing a
generally guided
something is going to prevent
the movement in towards a tantric style
of a tantric approach to meditating
because
in any guided session there's an
assumption that we're all starting
as um on the same platform or that we're
all
uh malleable in the same way
and from the sutra perspective that is
correct
that there are general answers from the
tantric perspective there are no general
answers and there are no
um there are no general guidelines it's
very difficult in some ways to have
when you look at tantra from the zog
chain perspective it's very difficult to
have this
um simple map
that applies to everybody
i mean you can but it's
more in the spirit of tantric approach
to become more
individually oriented and i think that's
probably why
in a lot of uh traditionally in
in vajrayana sanghas you'd have very
small groups
well this this kind of speaks to my
experience too right of like
uh there's a number of times like
especially when we first started talking
where i was looking for like very
specific answers from you right where i
was like here's my practice
this is what i'm running into and i'm so
used to there being like
a very specific well you do this in this
case you do that always an answer
yeah there's a very set specific answer
yeah
yeah yeah and with you it was more of
like
uh you know when you would respond to me
you'd usually you know
understand where the question was coming
from uh and then
allow me to kind of arrive at the
appropriate response to it uh that was
that that worked for me
and like very specifically it would be
you know i
realized from a lot of my past uh
concentration meditation was like the
the importance of being completely still
and upright and never moving and you're
just
composed throughout the entire thing um
and uh
and then you know realizing that you
know it's okay to adjust from time to
time like
there's there's just a naturalness to
the to tantra that feels
um yeah it has a natural quality that's
very individualized
right and you know for somebody who's
coming from different background
having that discipline and rigidity
might actually be really useful
it really really depends on who you are
as an individual and where
your frame of reference is you know
yeah well and i will say too that i
don't know if earlier in my
practice i could have started sitting
the
the undirected gene like i think i might
it might have
given up very soon because i wasn't
getting traction
you know that all of that right all that
uh
that container is very secure it creates
a foundation for you to start practice
on
um yeah and when you're starting out i
think if you've never meditated before
it's very useful to have very
clear supportive um
physical and and mental uh
set framework
yeah some some discipline is really good
to begin with as well
yeah a couple of hands raised uh doug i
think
you you might have been the first do do
you want to unmute yourself doug
question
oh it looks there you go hello
hello what wonderful to actually see you
in
in live uh stream uh charlie uh you too
you too yeah yeah my other name is
rinsing yeah
um i i'm you know i didn't really bump
into the notion of non-dualism and
dualism until about
three or four years ago and kind of like
um oh all the
the uh meta modern you know
uh emergence uh ideas i i've really had
a hard time
nailing down what people mean by it and
so over time i came up
with it without what i thought was
non-dualism or dualism referring to the
subject
object split and you're seeming to be
using it more as a
relational you know dichotomization
of the objective world which is kind of
really messing my
mind up oh and so i'm not sorry about
that
it's okay if my mind was was not in
alignment
you know if i really had arrived at the
wrong definition of dualism and
non-dualism
so i don't think there's a wrong is
there
[Laughter]
i don't know i mean uh it's really
interesting to hear you say this doug
i am sorry to kind of jump in there as
well
i i don't use the word nondual
myself i i probably do sometimes but i
i'm attempting to not use non-dual
and enlightenment and awakening i think
they've become so hashed
out in different contexts and
they just come to mean so many different
things um
and i'm tending to they're away from
from that terminology
sorry i kind of no no
i appreciate the conundrum that you're
attempting to
address by but um
the fact that people still use language
means that it would be nice to know what
they're pointing to
um and even if we don't have that for
enlightenment and other things i
i'm curious if you could give me a more
of a definition of what you mean by the
non-dual
or the dual dualism that you're talking
about
oh because i'm talking about dualism
doesn't mean that
um i'm aiming for non-dualism
uh non-dualism is it has kind of become
like a sort of opposite to dualism in
some way
um dualism
can shatter
into pluralities and multiplicities and
nuance and complexity and
[Music]
all kinds of things
the
the relationship is is asymptotic so
it's not like there's a thing that
you're heading towards that you can get
there's always more contextualization
there's always
more um
[Music]
movement into congruent activity
so you know if one were to frame things
in that kind of language if there being
an
end point um it's really difficult
it's like there isn't an end point there
are there's increasingly congruent
activity
and response and behavior
so the congruence is the thing
does that make some kind of sense i'm
close
i think i'm following but i'm not sure
can you use dualism and congruence in a
sentence
dualism and what sorry congruence
congruence can i you can i use dualism
and congruence in one sentence
so let's see
you can you can move from a dualist
frame of reference
into congruent activity
it is congruent activity how is that
related to non-dualism
did you get that out uh yeah yeah i'm
just i'm kind of thinking how
how does how to respond in a way that is
that makes some kind of sense um what
what do you want to be non-dual as soon
as you don't have
the dual the the polarities
then you have non-dualism uh that
doesn't mean that you have congruent
spontaneous activity
i mean what i'm trying to avoid is
framing things in terms of everything
being one
because things are both the same and
different there's distinction
and there is nebulosity and
empty quality to all um all phenomena
so
what we're not heading towards is some
kind of cosmic
transcendental world that is outside
the the world that we're in that is
somehow
causes this world to be illusory
does that make some kind of sense
totally appreciate what you're saying
um maybe let me
see if i can frame it more clearly um
when i was on meditation retreat at the
monastic academy and i had
more time to hang out in meditation
states i could walk around
and i could shift into a sense of unity
with all things
but there was still doug walking around
being unified with all things
and then there was also a state where
i would just you know i would just
disappear
and everything was just arising and
flowing and you know my hands moving
were no different
than the leaves on the trees or the wind
blowing and
you know my my sense of existence just
expanded
to all of it as opposed to this meat
thing that
i was and so i assumed that that's what
people referred to when they talk about
non-dual
that the subject object split kind of
disappeared
and you see i think people do yeah i i
think people do
use non-dual in that way that is not
the subject object split is
is kind of like a little bit of a red
herring i think i mean
there is relationship so we tend to want
to fix things into subject object
but this whole idea of an object and
focusing on an object yeah that's a very
cetric
idea that's not where that's not the
starting point
and buddhist tantra so if you don't have
that as a starting point then there's no
sort of strong relevance of
subjectivity and objectivity suddenly
becoming non-dual because
you know i mean they they
they were always nebulous
this is just a different frame of
reference i think in some ways
it sounds like a great experience though
well yeah and useful yeah
i mean there's just so many different
experiences we can have
i'm just trying to get a sense of what
people are pointing to when they use
different languages
and yeah i think that's really important
yeah
yeah i'm glad you do that thank you so
so thanks for trying to answer this
is as you have and i'll let you go back
to
the rest of what you were trying to
communicate thanks thank you
so i know we're running about on time we
have a ton of questions coming in and
i guess first off apologies to everybody
who is sending questions that we're not
able to
uh to field i think charlie and i were
thinking yeah let's let's
put something on the stoma maybe five or
six people will show up so uh
prepared for this um
[Music]
maybe when everybody's in in breakout
groups if you and i
don't go into a breakout group we could
filter through you know
pull the questions out or something like
that would that be useful
yeah i could probably pull us into our
own breakout group yeah
and and maybe i i'm wondering yeah i
don't know do you have a
kind of prompt or question that you
think might be uh fruitful for the group
and
you know even if we if we wanted to we
could allow for
a little bit more exploration because
things are still quite open yeah
right right we'll do the follow-up after
off recording
yeah i think that sounds great um i
would say in the practice groups really
uh discuss and focus
on application and whether this actually
has any
um salience or usefulness
in terms of where you're at now both in
meditation and
in your in life in general
experientially so focus on experience
and whether this
is pertinent in some way does that make
some sense
yeah uh
let me let me continue to look around uh
l if you wanted to i
know there's a few questions that are
still floating out there and i'll
continue to do some right okay i'm going
to take a look at the
chat uh
this is so here's a question from rory
uh rory are you here
yep hello rory um would you like to
say something about your question and
ask it
i have to remember which question it was
oh
practices other than cheney
well yeah i suppose in the context of
this
framework you were suggesting of
transition
from a citric approach
to a dojin influenced
tantric approach what
practices can people outside of
the structures of
the tibetan groups that are available
can they explore
i'm a little uh i'm used to asking
questions live so you'll hear that my
voice
i love your accent i i really like your
um thank you for asking the question
that's a great question
uh there i think meditation
wise the meditations that jared and i
are talking about
are called the four now jaws they do
come from
tibetan buddhism they are available in
the arrow
online email course that has a really
nice
uh week by week
instruction set and lots of different
exercises that you can try in your
meditation practice so i really strongly
recommend that as a good starting point
for the style of meditation
that we're talking about maybe somebody
could find that and put a link
in the chat i'm aware of that i did
did not follow it all the way through
and so that is a good starting point for
the meditation
in terms of the um
in terms of practice off the cushion
it just really depends where you're at
it's very difficult to generalize
um i could say something about if you
sense that there is some kind of uh
dullness
or you're feeling a bit depressed or
you're
if there's a sort of um
sense of not
being fully in touch with the world in
your environment and that
practices of sensation are very valuable
indeed and just noticing the texture of
things
noticing the texture and visual quality
of things noticing movement
so when you're out and about just really
honing in on movement
and the textural quality of movement
can be very conducive to
helping with the
the understanding of your own
relatedness
okay that's something to consider yeah
yeah do you want to say something about
where you're
at personally or not i mean don't don't
if you
if you don't want to but what
what what would you like to address is
there something
and feel free to say yeah i
don't want to um
i don't think i have much to to to add i
i have a
zen background a sort of background so
but
i let's say i i grappled with that and
and failed in some sense to uh find my
home in that tradition and she can taser
kind of
it won the battle on me and uh and then
recently i've returned to
uh inspired by shinzon's approach which
is much more
uh creative and playful but also uh
you know um enlightenment for dummies
kind of
you know and so i've enjoyed that and
enjoyed
maybe stepping out from chinsin's
approach into one that is more
more as you said more appreciative more
expansive
more yeah thanks for mentioning
appreciation that is a major
practice in this uh this stance
act of appreciation so you know if if
in in any situation there is there are
qualities that it's possible to
appreciate
you appreciate the tenor of something
you appreciate
textures and yeah
you can act you can engage in
appreciation as a practice at
any time
[Music]
yeah that's that's great thanks i think
maybe i'll leave it for somebody else
to ask a question yeah fix the breakouts
so we can jared well done you're amazing
um
so uh did you want to just kind of
quickly restate so the the main prompt
is here
you know talking about how some of this
might be applied to your
specific practice and maybe even just
orientation outside
that too because that would work yeah
okay great
all right we'll we'll throw you in there
and then i think what we'll do is we'll
do that for 15 minutes uh so that will
be at our 90 minute marker we'll come
back here
then we'll stop recording and we can
take some follow-up questions i think uh
charlie and i will stick around for a
bit cool
all right
um those who are still in here did you
guys rejoin and didn't get a
you didn't get anything well let's
have this be our unofficial breakout
room then so go ahead and
you feel free to update yourself
well i guess maybe any anybody feel like
uh starting kicking things off
uh in our large breakout uh group
yeah i i'd like to jump into something
if that's possible
and this one is reported just fyi oh
good
uh i'm if i knew i'd tell you on
facebook and i've had exchanges with
both of you hello
and um you're two of my faves
and my understanding is because i was
given a proper introduction to zog chen
back when it was
secret and it's not secret anymore and
that's something i wanted to talk about
like oh that
you know you buy the ancient secrets of
tibet on amazon these days and
the other thing is that you have to be
introduced to zog chen or mahamudra
in order to do tantra like that is the
proper
introduction and then and i might be
wrong so please correct me
and but some people just stick with
zochin and don't go through tantra
that's another thing i was
i was told so um if i'm incorrect
i'm actually looking for clarification
it's really interesting because it's
usually presented in the other way
around
that to approach zog chen you would
start with tantra and then work towards
but you know there are different
presentations in different lineages and
um kagyu sometimes has sort of mixture
of
mahamudra zobchan you know nyangmar and
kagyu
mix up you get lots of um
lineages within myanmar that present it
from a perspective of mahayana so
there's no um you know some people
when when they're coming from a
particular tradition they will
have learned that this is the correct
way to do it and
so that also is to be taken into
consideration like you kind of respect
somebody's
um perspective if that's if that's the
one that they're
using um but i don't think there is from
perspective of zogchen
because of the nature
of the stance it's not really possible
to say that things have to be in a
particular order
one of the mechanisms that obtained uses
is to
um in the root text of semis to
regard all yana's
as being method rather than as truth and
that that is a really
um interesting flip in the history of
buddhism it's the first time that
there's a kind of
um conscientiously meta approach to all
of the different
yarners
thank you thank you
i'm really interested did you oh carry
on yeah
i was going to ask about the secrecy
thing um oh yeah what
was was your i know your arrow tear um
was that
ever presented as a secret thing or
you don't talk about this or or was it
always open
no so i think what what has happened
so so two things the history of tibetan
monasticism
has um
created structures that would
then lead to certain esoteric practices
being regarded
as very secret and not available to
the general public or not available to
the ordinary monks or
whatever so there's that aspect and it's
secret in the sense that we understand
secret and then there's also this idea
of self-secrecy yes yeah
um which is that something is secret in
the sense
that it cannot be known until you know
it
yourself through experience and so it it
discovers itself to you at the point
that it becomes discoverable
and um therefore is no longer secret
so that is often taught as uh that is
what the secret
means and there's also secret in the
sense that there are a lot of
um traditional rituals and practices
which
are ostensibly one thing but that
um once you've
been around long enough or reached a
certain
style of practice or whatever that they
then come to have a different
application
and you can practice them in different
ways and that's not
necessarily always known like so for
example you could have
a practice that is
ostensibly a ritual
song or a group group practice
and then some people could be practicing
that as chip practice
while um still engaging in the group
and engaging with it as yogic song
so there's that kind of secrecy
as well so there are often different
layers of things but yeah as you say
pretty much everything is available
online
now i i think
something i would want to say about that
as well is that
there there is a way
in which secrecy is used
to
um
to prevent people from accessing
practices that they could have
in order to maintain a particular kind
of structure and
uh hierarchy and um
buy-in so i think it can be used in that
way as well
oh yeah yeah of course
yeah thank you charlie
yeah you're welcome andy has a question
about
initiation and direct transmission uh
are they important are they necessary
um and a follow-up question is
is there a wrong or perhaps
uh way of approaching this material that
is
so off base is to be detrimental
so the the second part of that question
you could approach anything in life in a
way that is so off
off track that is detrimental
so it's not the material it's the
approach
does that make some kind of sense like
yes totally yeah
yeah uh there are
you know there are ways that it is said
that tantra can be um
not right for some people at some time i
think that's true of any
any path and because they are
in some sense their systems there are
ways in which you can predict
that systems will fail or are more
likely to fail
so there are certain ways that tantra is
more likely to go wrong than sutra and
there's
certain ways that sutra is more likely
to go wrong
you know the kind of obvious way that
sutra fails is
splitting and then
you you split and you're you
intensify the split so much that there's
a sudden explosion
or you end up acting out
the negative side of the split
in your life in a surreptitious and
secret way because
you're trying to fit
into this sort of limited good pure
presentation or you you're kind of
committed to that in some way
and the the side that you're
repressing comes out in different ways
so that's the kind of typical
failure mode of sutra and then the the
predictable failure mode of tantra is um
insane ego power
trips yeah we've seen a lot of that over
the last few years and i think that you
know one of the reasons that
jared and i are even doing this is that
tibetan buddhism
has kind of exploded spectacularly
you know it's just
failed in that kind of predictable way
and how about the transmission direct
right yeah um so depending on the
framework so there are
in in buddhist tantra there are ritual
ways of initiation and
transmission so it's it's ritualized
into a
practice that very often is a group
practice and so that becomes
um a structure within which
the transmission is supposed to take
place and maybe it does maybe it doesn't
whatever and the zogchen informal
transmission
that is much more
something that is openly available
all the time and
there's uh a teaching
about a teaching called the five
certainties which are
you know certainty of time certainty
means
um kind of congruence like congruence of
place time teaching teacher
retinue and there's this idea
that transmission so the word
transmission
very literally it means
the passing of understanding from
one person to another one generation to
another
so it has these connotations of lineage
and of
um conscious maintaining
of knowledge in the experiential sense
so the experience of transmission is
very real
you know you can you can be
in a situation and suddenly there's this
kind of
aha moment and it's like you get
something it's very difficult to explain
exactly what that is what is happening
in that moment and
that is i think it's not well
described or documented usually
transmission is turned into this
um it's sort of reified in some sense
and it's you know it's made to be
um inevitable
in a traditional sense you can get these
um
the role of the teachers to transmit and
then if you're in the presence of the
teachers you
transmission can happen and there's a
sort of an inevitability that the
there's some sort of literal seed like
thing that they plant in you and then
it's gonna
sprout whatever so that's
i think metaphorical for the actual
experience of transmission which
is can be really extraordinary and it's
very real
but not essential necessarily to
um work with the material or to
it's not essential to work with the
material but i think it is at the heart
of the approach i think it's it's
something that
once you really engage with the material
and start applying
the perspective and the world view and
living
that view then it is something that
occurs
and it occurs as a natural result you
can't force it
but it it happens it's not like it's not
going to happen either
with application of the the approach
that's kind of the mechanism by which
zog chang comes to
uh manifest itself yeah
thank you yeah um
this is this is it's turning into
questions and answers and
um yeah i was going to be a fly on the
wall
kind of nosy i liked it um
yeah so so we are i i think everybody
should be back in the the main room now
um that's right so anybody who's been uh
listening to the recording
um thanks for thanks for tuning in and
um
thanks to again to the stoa uh and for
um for those who don't know this doe
runs on a gift economy so if you go to
the stoa.ca at the bottom there's
uh places to to direct your generosity
uh i'm a i'm a patron of theirs and
really love what peter's doing so
you know if you feel so inclined i would
encourage you to support this platform
as well
um that being said we're going to end
the recording here now and then we'll
kind of continue to see what happens
if anybody wants to stick around